Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
So today's דף Daf is ע"ג Ayin Gimmel and we're continuing this
discussion about somebody who gives a גט Get on the condition that
they will die from the illness that they are in the middle
of. The question is when is that framed as a condition and
when is that framed as after the illness, so then it's not
good because then it would be a גט לאחר מיתה. Get Le'achar
Misa. So we pick up on our דף ע"ג Daf Ayin Gimmel
73 and we pick up on ע"ב עמוד ב Ayin Beis Amud
Beis about 10 lines from the bottom, the two dots. זהו גיטך
מהיום אם מתי מחולי זה: Zehu Gitcha mehayom im mesni mecholiz zeh:
somebody says a perfectly formed תנאי, Tnai, this is your גט Get
as of today if I die from this illness. Everything is exactly
as explicit as we mean it to be. So now the question
is going to be when is that condition met or not met?
So the משנה Mishna says, אם עמד והלך בשוק, im omad vehalech
bashuk, if he got up and was able to walk around in
the marketplace and go outside, but then he fell ill again, he
relapsed and died, you don't say, well, you know, clearly this is
something new just because he went and walked around in the marketplace.
You assess and you determine by doctors and I don't know how,
and if you determine that it was still as a result of
the original illness and he was relapsing back into the original illness
and the original illness had never left to some then it would
be a good גט, Get, otherwise if it's something new it would
not be a good גט. Get. That's the משנה. Mishna. So let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues to sort of clarify
and push this point. אמר רב הונא גיטו כמתנתו. Amar Rav Huna:
Gito Ke-matnaso. We've seen this statement of רב הונא Rav Huna before:
a גט Get of a person on his deathbed is like a
gift of a person on his deathbed, a מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnas
Shchiv Mera, when he's trying to sort of bequeath his property. מה
מתנתו אם עמד חוזר, Ma matnaso im omad chozer, the same way
by a gift of a שכיב מרע Shchiv Mera if he gets
better from the illness, he was there lying in his deathbed distributing
his property and then he recovered, so it would automatically be whatever
he gave you would return, fine, we're not getting there right there,
anyway the gift would be reversed.
אף גיטו אם עמד חוזר, Af gito im omad chozer, so the
same way by a גט Get if he gets better it would
be reversed. Now I want to get back I'm going to get
back to that and unpack it in a minute, but let's just
read the next line.
ומה גיטו אף על גב דלא פירש, U-ma gito af al gav
delo peireish, even by this גט Get even though he did not
fully say his statement. What does it mean he didn't fully say
his statement? כיון דאמר כתבו אף על גב דלא אמר תנו. Kivan
de'amar 'kisvu' af al gav delo amar 'tenu'. As long as he
said
write, even if he didn't say, okay so, even though he didn't
say give it. Meaning you might remember there's an earlier set of
משניות Mishnayos that normally writing it doesn't mean writing it let me
put it in my pocket, let me have it ready, but if
somebody is on their deathbed or somebody is being taken out to
be executed or somebody is going on a faraway journey, in all
those cases we interpret the words write it to mean write it
and give it. So the same way that's true by somebody on
the deathbed, אף
מתנתו
כיון דאמר תנו אף על גב דלא קני מידו, af matnaso kivan
de'amar 'tenu' af al gav delo kani miyado, a gift of a
שכיב מרע, Shchiv Mera, he has to say give it to
so-and-so, even though they didn't do a קנין Kinyan it's still binding.
Now both of these statements need unpacking and I'm going to start
with the second one because we're going to sort of discuss that
and then put it aside because our focus is going to be
on the first one. So the second one the question is you
don't need, who is this, רב הונא Rav Huna to tell you
that a מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shchiv Mera doesn't need a קנין.
Kinyan. That's the whole הלכה Halacha on מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Shchiv
Mera. Somebody distributes it verbally on their deathbed and that counts and
it's binding. So what's the חידוש Chiddush to say oh, you give
it, you don't have to do a קנין? Kinyan? So תוספות Tosafot
points out that's not really the point. The real point is is
that what רב הונא Rav Huna is saying, that second part of
the statement, is anytime by a גט Get we פוסק pasken that
כתבו kisvu means כתבו ותנו, kisvu u-tenu, that we see that the
circumstances are ones in which we interpret that that's that he's afraid
he's going to die and he means to give it, so whether
he's on his deathbed or he's being taken out to be executed
or he's going away on a faraway journey, whatever those cases were
before that that's the context in which write it in a certain
context we interpret the word כתבו kisvu to mean כתבו ותנו, kisvu
u-tenu, that context works for מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Shchiv Mera. If
so somebody found themselves in a similar context, somebody was taken out
to be executed and says give my property to this person and
my property to that person, right, even though somebody's going to say
well you're not a שכיב מרע, Shchiv Mera, you're not on your
deathbed, the Rabbis only said מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Shchiv Mera. So
רב הונא Rav Huna is telling you no, the same cases that
work that כתבו kisvu means תנו, tenu, those cases work for מתנת
שכיב מרע Matnas Shchiv Mera and those are the contexts in which
a verbal gift counts as a gift. So that's the point of
the second part of the statement. That's not our focus but just
that's important to clarify because obviously we know that מתנת שכיב מרע
Matnas Shchiv Mera doesn't need a קנין. Kinyan. Now how about the
first part of the statement? Here we have an interesting debate of
רש"י ותוספות Rashi and Tosafot and it's going to affect how they're
going to interpret the rest of the גמרא. Gemara. I'm going to
follow רש"י Rashi just for simplicity's sake but I'll tell you the
debate. רש"י Rashi says what רב הונא Rav Huna is introducing is
a huge חידוש Chiddush based on the משנה. Mishna. You look at
our משנה Mishna and it sounds pretty clear that if a guy
were to give a גט Get there lying on
his
זה גיטך מהיום אם מתי וכולי. Ze gittech mehayom im mati v'chulei.
ורש"י Rashi says no, רב הונא Rav Huna is coming along and
saying just like if a guy is on his deathbed and give
a great gift and is distributing his property and it’s implicitly understood
he means in case I die, so if a guy gives a
גט get on his deathbed without saying any condition, it's as if
he said this should take effect on the condition that I die
from this illness. So basically what רש"י Rashi understands is what רב
הונא Rav Huna is doing is saying that all these conditions in
the משנה Mishna are only if you bother to say something, and
that's when you could actually trip yourself up if you frame it
in the wrong way. But if you just don't say anything, then
the condition is implicit. Okay, that's the way what רש"י Rashi is
reading it. So אף גיטו אם עמד חוזר Af gitto im amad
chozar means that you don't need any condition and אם עמד חוזר.
im amad chozar. תוספות Tosafos says that that's not what he's saying
at all, לאו חס ושלום, lav chas veshalom, you need to make
an explicit condition and that all רב הונא Rav Huna is saying
is is that when do we say the condition is not met
by a גט, get, meaning when do we say that you didn't
die מחולי זה? me'choli zeh? So what he would be saying is
as soon as the guy's able to get up out of the
bed, then he's not considered to have died מחולי זה. me'choli zeh.
Well no, and that goes directly against our משנה, Mishna, which is
what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. Our משנה Mishna says
what do you mean, the משנה Mishna says he gets up and
whatever and he falls back down and you know he has a
relapse maybe he did die מחולי זה. me'choli zeh. And the גמרא
Gemara says but תוספות Tosafos says that רב הונא Rav Huna is
saying no I'm telling you whenever he gets up it's no longer
מחולי זה. me'choli zeh. Okay, so according to תוספות Tosafos all רב
הונא Rav Huna is doing is telling you what condition, what circumstances
make it that we decide that it's not מחולי זה. me'choli zeh.
But according to רש"י Rashi it's a much bigger חידוש. chiddush. It’s
that you don't even have to make a stipulation, the stipulation is
implicit, okay, that it's always אם ימות מחולי זה. im yamut me'choli
zeh. Yes, so exactly, so when רש"י Rashi says ולא מיבעיא היכא
דאמר אם מתי, velo mibaya heicha de'amar im mati, what compels him
to read it that way? Well, just because of A because רב
הונא Rav Huna said
you know because A he's making a comparison to שכיב מרע, sh'chiv
mera, so in שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera you don't have to make
it explicit, so if you're just saying the same way שכיב מרע
sh'chiv mera you know gets better, you know אף על פי דלא
פירש af al pi de'lo peireish like he
radically, like even... well yeah because the comparison to a שכיב מרע,
sh'chiv mera, the שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera didn't have an explicit תנאי.
tnai. Also as the גמרא Gemara continues, in some ways it reads
better according to רש"י, Rashi, so he might be impacted by which
reads fits into the continued discussion. But I just you know but
he's basically but he's saying like just a straight comparison. Oh I
had a short question just if you don't mind yesterday. Just forget
this case where he gets up and walks around, right? Just from
like the straight case where he makes the good condition.
Yeah. So she becomes divorced retroactively as of that day until finally
he dies. Yeah. But let's say she was married to a כהן
Kohen and in the meantime... okay that's a coming up משנה Mishna
later today. What's going to be the story in the meantime? מה
היא באותן הימים? Mah hi be'otan hayamim? Okay, that's good, that's the
משנה Mishna aspect of that question. Okay, yeah, yes. I have a
feeling this is
somewhat different for שכיב מרע. sh'chiv mera. Your property is under the
jurisdiction of the בית דין Beis Din from the beginning. The whole
thing is not subject to like דאורייתא De'oraisa right as for a
גט. get. Right, so it's true, גט get is a דאורייתא, De'oraisa,
so obviously he has to actually physically give the גט. get. It's
not like the words can turn into a קנין kinyan like they
can by שכיב מרע. sh'chiv mera. But what you're saying is that
so this idea that you don't have to say the condition, what
רש"י Rashi is assuming reading it this way to רב הונא Rav
Huna is not that that's like oh that's חז"ל's Chazal חידוש. chiddush.
חז"ל's Chazal חידוש chiddush by שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera is the words
effect a קנין. kinyan. But the idea that it's conditional on the
fact that it's assuming he's going to die, רש"י Rashi would say
based on his read that's not a חידוש chiddush of חז"ל, Chazal,
that's just an implicit תנאי tnai in the situation. So that works
even for a דאורייתא גט, De'oraisa get, right? That's just assumed to
be his
דעת. da'as. I'm sorry, you're saying רש"י Rashi is saying the whole
of this is a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera essentially? And not necessarily
be on his deathbed? It can be in the hospital, like having
an appendicitis or whatever. No,
no, no, no, only a case where the guy's on his deathbed
and where by a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera we would say that
it's a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera is a case where
we read that implicit תנאי tnai into the giving of a גט.
get. Okay, so the cases of שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera are cases
where we see an implicit תנאי tnai in the giving of a
גט. get. Yes. Is the comparison between גט get and שכיב מרע
sh'chiv mera is the קנין kinyan is implied and are we doing
the apparent comparison that the תנאי tnai is implied? Yes, so doing
קנין kinyan is what's being... okay, let's take a look at how
the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Now we're going to have a problem though because whether the
point is that he explicitly said אם מתי מחולי זה im mati
me'choli zeh or רב הונא Rav Huna is saying even if he
said nothing it's like he said אם מתי מחולי זה, im mati
me'choli zeh, the problem still is going to be that רב הונא
Rav Huna says that when you get up and walk around, you're
done, it's בטל. batel. So what about the משנה? Mishna? The משנה
Mishna doesn't have it בטל batel as soon as the guy walks
around. So let's take a look. תנן *Tnan*, and we learned the
משנה mishnah *mishna*, זה גיטך מהיום אם מתי mehayom im mati. מחולי
זה meicholi zeh. *ze gittech mehayom im meisi macholi zeh* ועמד והלך
בשוק *v'amad v'halach bashuk* וחלה ומת *v'chala v'meit*. אומדין אותו *omdin oso*
אם מחמת חולי choli, הראשון מת הרי זה גט harei zeh get.
*im machmas choli harishon meis harei zeh get* אם לאו אינו גט
eino get. *im lav eino get*. Okay, he walks up, he gets
around, he falls back, he relapses. You determine if it's still מחולי
זה meicholi zeh, *mecholi zeh*. That's against רב הונא Rav Huna, *Rav
Huna*. רב Rav הונא *Rav Huna* said, whether with or without an
explicit condition, רב הונא *Rav Huna* said when you get up and
walk around, it's no longer מחולי זה meicholi zeh *mecholi zeh*. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says אי אמרת *ei amart* אם מחמת חולי
זה machmat choli zeh *im machmas choli zeh* according to רב הונא
*Rav Huna*, למה לי אומדנא *lama li omdana*? What's the whole idea
of making an assessment? הרי עמד amad, *harei amad*, he got up
and then it's no longer defined as מחולי זה meicholi zeh *mecholi
zeh*. אמר מר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה דרבה *Amar Mar brei de'Rav
Yosef mishmeih de'Rava* שניטק מחולי לחולי mecholi lecholi, *shenitak mecholi l'choli*. Ah,
the משנה mishnah, *mishna*, you're right, if he was completely healthy and
then or like completely, you know, there was no, and then he
walked around, that's רב הונא's *Rav Huna's* case. When the משנה mishnah,
*mishna* says he got up and walked around and he relapses and
we could still call it מחולי זה meicholi zeh, *mecholi zeh*, that's
when he was still struggling with a different problem. Okay, like he
had pneumonia and then it turned into, I don't know, whatever.
I'm trying to think about what an example would be. Like okay,
he's no longer, he no longer has signs of pneumonia, but he's
still got a, give me some. An infection. And he's still got
an infection. Okay, and then he relapses and the pneumonia comes back.
So in that case, that's not, that's a case where the משנה
mishnah *mishna* is talking about. רב הונא *Rav Huna* says you have
to be an עמד amad *amad*, right, you have to totally be
like, if you're totally free of any type of an illness, then
anything afterwards is considered to be a different story new. You know,
it's sort of like, okay, it's a bad comparison, but let's say
you go ahead, you know, it's raining out right now, right? Let's
say you go ahead and you make a ברכה *bracha* right about,
you know, about what? Yeah, yeah, you know, thunder. Yeah, עושה מעשה
בראשית *oseh ma'aseh bereishis* שכחו וגבורתו מלא עולם *shekocho u'gevuraso malei olam*.
And then like it stops raining for a while, then it starts
raining again, and then you have more thunder. You have to make
another ברכה *bracha*? Like is it, when does it like, you know,
like, is it just like there was a... so anyway, so what
the גמרא's gemara. *Gemara's* saying is that when the משנה Mishnah. *mishna*
says he can get out of the חולי *choli* and relapse and
be the same thing, that's if there's some continuation of חולי *choli*
throughout, maybe a different חולי *choli*, but some continuation of חולי *choli*
throughout which never creates a break. When רב הונא *Rav Huna* says
if he got better, it's a break and it doesn't matter what
happened afterwards, that's if there was a period of no חולי *choli*.
So that's the גמרא's gemara. *Gemara's* answer. Okay, so the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* says like this. Okay, הרי זה גט get. אם לאו אינו
גט get. ואי אמרת *harei zeh get im lav eino get v'ei
amart*... okay, אמר מר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה דרבה שניטק מחולי לחולי
mecholi lecholi *Amar Mar brei de'Rav Yosef mishmeih de'Rava shenitak mecholi l'choli*.
והא עמד קתני *V'ha amad katani*. You can't say the משנה Mishnah
*mishna* is that he's still dealing with some illness, because it says
he stood up. It sounds like he's totally better. No, אמר מחולי
זה meicholi zeh ונפל לחולי אחר *Amar mecholi zeh v'nafal l'choli acher*.
It means he got out of one illness but he's still dealing
with another illness. והלך בשוק קתני *V'halach bashuk katani*. But it says
he's walking around, and presumably that he's free of illness. No, הלך
על משענתו *halach al mishanto*. He went out
on his cane. Exactly, exactly. So alright, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
says, so then if that's true, what's the חידוש chiddush, *chiddush* of
the משנה Mishna. *mishna*? Because the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of the משנה
Mishna, *mishna* read simply is like, it looks like he's 100 percent
better and nevertheless it could still be מחמת חולי זה *machmas choli
zeh* if he falls sick again. Okay, according to you, what's the
חידוש *chiddush* of the משנה Mishna *mishna*? You're reinterpreting all the conditions
of the משנה *mishna* to say that he still looks, he's still
struggling along. So what's the חידוש *chiddush*? Even with that, you're still
ill, we still don't say it's מחולי זה meicholi zeh. *mecholi zeh*,
might be. Ah, so that's the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. But the way
you read the משנה *mishna*, it's not like it looks like he's
better, it's still he's still struggling along. So what's the חידוש *chiddush*?
The גמרא gemara *Gemara* says the חידוש *chiddush* is what Michael said.
דהא קמ"ל *de'ha ka mashma lan*, and in that case the חידוש
*chiddush* is דהלך על משענתו הוא דבעינן אומדנא *de'halach al mishanto hu
de'ba'inan omdana*. So that if he's going around on his stick or
whatever, then we need to assess because then maybe it's something else
if he goes and has a relapse. אידך *Idach*, if he doesn't,
if he's not even walking around on his stick or whatever, אומדנא
נמי לא בעינן *omdana nami lo ba'inan*. He doesn't even need an
אומדנא *omdana*. Okay, so the חידוש *chiddush* is that you might have
said look, if he's just walking around on his stick or whatever
it's ודאי vadai, *vaday* מחולי זה meicholi zeh, *mecholi zeh*. לאו ודאי
vadai *lav vaday*. Okay, there was enough of an improvement that it
might not be מחולי זה *mecholi zeh*, we'll have to assess. Okay,
that's the חידוש *chiddush* of the משנה *mishna*. Alright, but אין in,
הכי נמי *ein hachi nami*, if he really got better for a
while, then it would never, we would never say if there was
a relapse that it was מחולי זה *mecholi zeh*.
Bit of a tricky thing, right? He could be so to speak
on his way to getting
better, but not completely better. So he's got the stick so to
say, the metaphor. Right.
It's hard to assess whether he's going to relapse. I understand, I
understand. So now what have we said? We have said like this.
The פשט *pshat* of the משנה *mishna* is it doesn't matter if
it looked like it was a full recovery, like I mean think
about a cancer case, right? I mean what does that mean? Let's
say somebody actually is dying of cancer and saying, you know, and
doing this case and then actually it goes into remission and five
years later they die of the same cancer. Is it מחולי זה
*mecholi zeh*, you know? So I don't know. So the פשט of
the משנה might be that it would be, it doesn't matter if
there's a break now, if it ultimately was מחולי זה. So Rav
Huna says no, I'm sorry. Once there was a period of real
עמד, a freeness of illness for a period, at least externally, right?
They didn't have tests that they could run, whatever, then anything else
would be considered something different. And then the question is how do
you fit it into the משנה, and the גמרא gemara basically says,
all right, it doesn't work so well in the משנה, we'll have
to say in the משנה that the only opportunity to say that
it's מחמת חולי זה is when somebody was
basically dealing, מחולי לחולי, and there was not a full recovery. But
that way it's still possible that that's a case where it still
might be מחולי זה, it might not, and we have to assess.
All right, so let's take a look now at the גמרא. gemara
Okay, שמע מינה shma mina says the גמרא. Gemara This comes so
we infer from this, we infer from this that שכיב מרע שניתק
מחולי לחולי מתנתו מתנה. shchiv mei'ra shenitak mecholi lecholi matnato matana. Can
we infer from this that שכיב מרע, shchiv mei'ra, that you're saying
that
מחולי זה would constitute מחולי זה if he never actually got up
from the bed? But if there he was, it looked like he
was dying of pneumonia and he wound up dying of an infection,
but he was always in the bed the whole time. Would that
count for שכיב מרע? shchiv mei'ra? Would his מתנה matana be good?
Right? Basically it sounds like what you're saying, that as long as
there was never a period of getting up, even if it switched
from one to the next, it's all considered to be part of
the same process. Especially that happens nowadays, people might die of an
infection or another secondary secondary thing, but the secondary things were all
a result of the primary. All right, so anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says is that what you now mean to say? By שכיב
מרע shchiv mei'ra it would be good? אין, in, yes, דאמר רבי
אלעזר משמיה דרב שכיב מרע שניתק מחולי לחולי מתנתו מתנה. de'amar Rabi
Elazar mishmei deRav shchiv mei'ra shenitak mecholi lecholi matnato matana. Okay, so
what have we now said according to Rav Huna? Guy that gets
fully up
and whatever happens later is considered something new. It doesn't matter if
it's מחולי זה, it's not considered מחולי זה if a guy gets
up and it's full recovery. If a guy is ניתק מחולי לחולי
nitak mecholi lecholi and doesn't get up at all, it's considered מחולי
זה. It's considered מחולי זה, even if you'll say that really in
the end it was the infection and not the pneumonia or not
the cancer. If however in a middle case where it was מחולי
לחולי and he was schlepping around and he got up, that's when
we have to assess whether it was מחולי ראשון mecholi rishon or
מחולי שני. mecholi sheni. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. רבה ורבא לא סבירא להו הא דרב הונא. Rabba veRava lo
svira lehu ha deRav Huna. They don't hold of Rav Huna that
getting up automatically means it's something new. Now, why not? You could
have just said cause it might still be the חולי ראשון. choli
rishon. But the גמרא Gemara gives a secondary reason. גזירה שמא יאמרו
יש גט לאחר מיתה. gezeirah shema yomru yesh get le'achar mita. We're
afraid that people will say יש גט לאחר מיתה. yesh get le'achar
mita. Now, how are people going to say יש גט לאחר מיתה?
yesh get le'achar mita? Where is that coming from? So רש"י Rashi
explains the following way. This is where רש"י's Rashi explanation works better.
Meaning he thought he got better and then like it would be
if you still say it's okay then יש גט לאחר מיתה. yesh
get le'achar mita. But what is it לאחר מיתה? le'achar mita? They
might say תנאים tna'im don't work, but where are they going to
say יש גט לאחר מיתה? yesh get le'achar mita? He got better
and it was a good גט. get, What does that mean לאחר
מיתה? le'achar mita? He's better, he's walking around. It was still a
good גט. get, And it's not לאחר מיתה. le'achar mita. No, but
then he died, right? Meaning then you see him die. Is that
exactly right? Anyway, let me tell you
how רש"י Rashi explains it. It's not as simple as you think.
Okay, so what's the concern about יש גט לאחר מיתה? yesh get
le'achar mita? So רש"י—יגרא—רש"י's explanation works better. Because remember רש"י Rashi said
let's bracket the עמד point that the גמרא Gemara has been focusing
on, what constitutes something new. רש"י Rashi basically says that the basic
חידוש, the primary חידוש of Rav Huna really was that by a
גט, get, even if you didn't say anything, it counts as if
you made a תנאי, tnai, right? So the guy's on his deathbed,
he doesn't say anything, he gives the גט, get. and it works.
So here's—I mean and then it's considered to be conditional on if
he dies. So רש"י Rashi says that's what רבא ורבה Rava veRabba
are responding to, because look at what's going to happen. Guy says
nothing, he gives a
גט, get. okay? In scenario number one, the guy dies and it's
a good גט. get In scenario number second, the guy gets better
and it's not a good גט. get You and me that are
looking at that, and also because of the parallel to שכיב מרע,
shchiv mei'ra, right, we're saying I don't understand. Why is it? In
case one it was a—he just died and it was good, here
he got better it didn't—it wasn't good? Like there was no condition,
what's happening? Oh, it must be that he said the גט get
should take effect after he dies, right? When he's giving a גט
get on his שכיב מרע, shchiv mei'ra, it's like he wants it
to take effect after he dies. And therefore in one case he
died, it took effect, the other case he didn't die, it didn't
take effect. Right? So we might read it that way since the
תנאי tnai isn't explicit. We should easily read it as that what's
going on here is the timing of the גט get and not
making the גט get conditional. So therefore they say we can't let
this—if the תנאי tnai isn't explicit, we cannot allow there to be
an implicit תנאי. tnai. It'll lead to misunderstanding. The problem is that's
very nice, that's a rabbinic concern. How do you stop a גט
get from working because of that? Or actually—right. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara now asks. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי איכא מידי
דמדאורייתא לא הוי גיטא? umi ika midi demide'oraita lo havay gita? Is
there something that דאורייתא de'oraita it's not a גט get, that implicitly
there really is a תנאי tnai here? ומשום גזירה umishum gezeira and
because of this גזירה gezeira that people are not going to see
the תנאי tnai and hear the תנאי tnai and they'll misinterpret what's
going on, שרינן אשת איש לעלמא? sharinan eshet ish l'alma? We'll make
this woman who really is a married woman, we'll make her considered
to be a divorced woman, right? Just think about what's going to
happen. He's going to get better. Okay, he gave her גט get,
on his deathbed and he gets better. And he says, oh so
now I didn't want it to take effect, that was my implicit
תנאי. tnai. Sorry, you gave her the גט, get she's free to
remarry. So we're going to let this woman who דאורייתא d'oraita should
be married to the first guy because there was an implicit תנאי,
tnai, and we're going to ignore the implicit תנאי tnai and let
her remarry? So they're saying that it I thought he was saying
the opposite, that we're not going to let it be a good
גט, get, therefore she stays married. No, if you gave a גט
get without making an explicit תנאי, tnai, then we're just saying you
gave a גט, get period, end of story. That's what it looks
like. It looks like there was no תנאי. tnai. Now, of course,
what's funny is they could have just disagreed in principle. They could
have said, I'm sorry, I don't think that there's an implicit תנאי
tnai here. Right, that's what would be what we would have said.
But no, the גמרא Gemara is saying is it doesn't you didn't
say a תנאי, tnai, it was not implicit, so we're just going
to say you gave a גט get at-all, period, end of story.
Okay. So גמרא Gemara, says, I don't get it, but דאורייתא d'oraita
there was a תנאי tnai and she's not divorced and we're going
to say it's like it's ignore the תנאי? tnai? So גמרא Gemara,
says, ומשום umishum אין, in, yes, so I'm sorry לא משום גזירה
שרינן אשת איש לעלמא? lo mishum gezeira sharinan eshet ish l'alma? אין,
in, yes. כל דמקדש אדעתא דרבנן מקדש ואפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה. kol
d'mekadesh ada'ata d'rabbanan mekadesh v'afkinu rabbanan l'kidushin minei. Now he's going to
take out this standard answer about these types of cases. Yes, whoever
gets married does it on the on the like, you know, on
the with the implicit agreement of חז"ל, Chazal, and therefore the Rabbis
have the power to annul the marriage. Okay, and therefore, so it's
true, דאורייתא d'oraita the גט get, didn't work because there was a
תנאי, tnai, but in this case we'll annul the marriage. אמר ליה
רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, תינח דקדש
בכספא. teinach d'kadash b'chaspa. That's fine if he does קידושי כסף kiddushei
kessef because maybe then they can use like הפקר בית דין הפקר
hefker beis din hefker and make it that the money was never
his. קדש בביאה מאי איכא למימר? kadash b'vi'ah mai ika l'meimar? Let's
say they קידושין kiddushin with sex, what are they going to do?
So he's
going to say אמר ליה, amar lei, דשווייה לבעילתו בעילת זנות. deshavyei
l'vi'ato bi'at zenut. The Rabbis have the power to define the frame,
you know, the context of the act. So they'll say the context
of the act was that that was just premarital sex, it wasn't
a מעשה קידושין, ma'aseh kiddushin, extramarital sex.
And therefore they will since it's all is based on the framing,
the lens of the Rabbis, they'll say we refuse to look at
it as if there was an act of קידושין kiddushin here. And
therefore that's how they'll solve it. Now of course the interesting thing,
like I'll just remind you, you know, this does sound like a
pretty radical solution, is רמב"ן Ramban actually points out that pretty much
in all the cases where the גמרא Gemara uses ואפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין
מיניה, v'afkinu rabbanan l'kidushin minei, there actually was a גט get, that
was there and the problem was something something to do with the
דעת da'as of the husband. Like you might remember the classic case
we had about the husband that was מבטל לשליח שלא בפניו. mevatel
l'shaliach shelo befanav. The problem was something the husband was choosing to
do. So here too, there was a גט, get the problem was
we're saying there was an implicit תנאי tnai and we don't like
the idea of the implicit תנאי. tnai. So what the רמב"ן Ramban
says is really ואפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה v'afkinu rabbanan l'kidushin minei is
we really don't do הפקעת קידושין. hafka'as kiddushin. What we really do
is we use it as a threat and we say to the
guy, listen, if you don't change your דעת da'as implicitly this is
what we're saying if you don't change your דעת, da'as, then we're
going to be מפקע mafki'a the קידושין kiddushin and you'll have wound
up these last 20 years doing בעילת זנות. bi'at zenut. And that's
the sting. Right, clearly since you wouldn't want to turn your קידושין
kiddushin into your whole life into בעילת זנות bi'at zenut and all
of that, we must say that deep down you really don't want
to be making the תנאי tnai here. You really don't want to
be מבטל לשליח שלא בפניו. mevatel l'shaliach shelo befanav. Okay, so what
the רמב"ן Ramban really says what we're doing here is we're really
redefining what the husband's דעת da'as is. We're so therefore that's at
least I think that's a more satisfying explanation. Like here the point
was that we were saying there's an implicit תנאי. tnai. רב and
רבא Rava don't like the implicit תנאי tnai because even if it's
true that that maybe is presumably his דעת, da'as, it's just going
to cause us headache because it's not explicit. So what we wind
up saying is we refuse to recognize the implicit תנאי. tnai. Right,
that's a lot easier to say than to say ואפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין
מיניה. v'afkinu rabbanan l'kidushin minei. So the רמב"ן Ramban is saying that
that's what it means. Because we have the power to do הפקעת
קידושין, hafka'as kiddushin, that gives us the power to say we refuse
to recognize the implicit תנאי tnai here. Yeah, but so the understanding
is it could have gone the other way. Instead of saying okay
I don't recognize your תנאי tnai it's a good גט, get could
have said there was no גט get? and you are still married.
Yeah, but that would be also like bizarre to people. So what?
So somebody gives a גט get and it's not a good גט?
get? He gave a גט get, on his deathbed, it's not a
good גט? get Well, it depends on the תנאי tnai that was
never met. But there was no תנאי, tnai, that's the whole problem,
people aren't seeing the תנאי, tnai, everything's implicit. They're looking at things,
they see the guy they heard him saying the גט, get I
mean they heard that a guy gave a גט get on his
deathbed. Whatever, there's a presumption that if there was some תנאי tnai
they would know about it, there was no תנאי, tnai, they heard
about the circumstances. Did you hear that this guy is giving גט
get on his deathbed and the Rabbis just threw it out, they
just disqualified it? Yeah, I heard another case like that last week,
I gave a גט get, and the Rabbis just disqualified it, what's
going on? Right, so at least the The simplest thing to say
is he gives a גט get *get*, he doesn't make a תנאי
tnai, *tnai*, it's a good גט get, *get*, end of story. Okay?
And that's what they say, we refuse to recognize his דעת *da'at*.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, so that
was a really interesting discussion based number one based on what constitutes
חולי זה *choli zeh* and not חולי זה *choli zeh*, the עמד
*amad* part of רב הונא'ס *Rav Huna's* statement; and number two, do
we say that on the deathbed even for a גט get *get*,
there's an implicit תנאי tnai *tnai*, and if we do say there's
an implicit תנאי tnai. *tnai*, maybe are we but what about the
you know sort of communal consequences of that and maybe we're just
going to ignore it and override it. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. In the case on the deathbed so to
speak then he gets he gets better, he doesn't die. Yeah, exactly.
That's well that's the case you have to worry about. Yeah, exactly.
But wait so one second so and she doesn't get married she
doesn't get married in the meantime, she does not get married. Right.
He gets better. Right. According to that they need they need חופה
*chuppah* again, they need קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* again? So he gives a
גט get *get* on his deathbed, he gets better. According to what,
רב *Rav* and רבא Rava. *Rava*? He didn't make a תנאי tnai
*tnai* then nothing then it's a גט get *get* she's divorced. He'd
even given her a גט get *get* they've been married so to
speak for for twenty years. Yeah. Yeah, whatever. To continue living together
he doesn't want ביאת זנות znut. *bi'at zenut* he has to I
mean if he's a כהן *kohen* it's a problem but if it's
otherwise then they get remarried. Yeah. Yeah, but that's what I'm saying
is it shouldn't be a good גט get *get*, like come on.
I understand, תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan: *Tanu Rabbanan*, זה גיטך מהיום אם
מתי מחולי זה *zeh gittech mehayom im mati mecholi zeh*. A guy
says, this is your גט get *get* again he says a perfectly
formulated תנאי tnai *tnai*. This is your גט get *get* as of
today if I die from this illness. ונפל הבית עליו *venafal habayit
alav*, and then the house collapses on him. Right, exactly. Oh, או
הכישו נחש *o hechisho nachas*, or a snake bites him. אינו גט
get *eino get*, it's not good because he said מחולי זה *mecholi
zeh*, from this illness. He didn't die from this illness. Okay, אם
לא אעמוד מחולי זה ונפל עליו הבית או הכישו נחש *im lo
amod mecholi zeh venafal alav habayit o hechisho nachash*, if I don't
recover from this illness and the house collapses on him or the
snake bites him, הרי זה גט get *harei zeh get*. It's a
גט get. *get* because he never recovered from the illness. Now to
us that makes total sense, brilliant, right? The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* does
not understand the difference between the two cases. Now תוספות Tosafot's *Tosafot*,
the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says, מאי שנא רישא reisha ומאי שנא סיפא
seifa. *mai shena reisha u-mai shena seifa*. I don't understand. I know,
so neither does תוספות *Tosafot*. Look at תוספות *Tosafot*. מאי שנא רישא
reisha, ומאי שנא סיפא sifa. *mai shena reisha u-mai shena seifa* says
תוספות *Tosafot*, בירושלמי מפרש טעמא רבה איכא *b'Yerushalmi meforash ta'ama rabba ika*.
There's a very big difference. דברישא הרי לא מת מחולי זה *d'be-reisha
harei lo met mecholi zeh*, in the first case the illness is
not what he died as a result of, אבל בסיפא אם לא
אעמוד קאמר *aval be-seifa im lo amod ka-amar*, but in the second
case, "if I don't recover" he said, והרי לא עמד *ve-harei lo
amod*, he didn't recover, דלא עמד משמע בין על ידי חולי בין
על ידי דבר אחר *d'lo amod mashma bein al yedei choli bein
al yedei davar acher*. It just means I didn't recover, it's not
saying the cause of the lack of recovery. Okay, אבל גמרא Gemara
שלנו אינו סובר חילוק זה *aval Gemara shelanu eino sover chilluk zeh*.
אלא בכולם משמע ליה שימות מתוך חולי זה *ela be-chulam mashma lei
she-yamut mitoch choli zeh*. For whatever reason the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands
מחולי זה *mecholi zeh* does not mean as a result of, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands מחולי זה *mecholi zeh* means during this illness.
If I do not recover, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* reads both
cases as, if I do not recover
during this illness. So if for both of them are, I die
during this illness, what's the difference? In both cases he died during
the illness, in both cases it should be, you know, you know,
it should be good. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מאי שנא
רישא ומאי שנא סיפא *mai shena reisha u-mai shena seifa*, in both
cases he died during the illness. So שלחו מתם shalchu mitam, *shalchu
mitam*, so they sent from there in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel, *Eretz
Yisrael*, אכלו ארי אין לנו *achlu ari ein lanu*. But we don't,
you know, we don't hold of the case of being eaten by
a lion. Now what does that mean? What? So what that means
is, where what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is reading this as opposed
to the simple sense of the ברייתא braisa. *braita* which we just
said, which is a simple question of technically was the תנאי tnai
*tnai* satisfied or not, did you say as a result of or
during, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* interprets it as a question of יש
אונס בגיטין yesh oness begittin או אין אונס בגיטין ein oness begittin.
*yesh ones b'gittin o ein ones b'gittin*, which is in general a
question of יש אונס oness. *yesh ones*, which means if I make
a condition and the condition was met but it was only met
because of circumstances outside of my control, is it considered like the
condition was met because that's not what I really meant. So the
standard case in the גמרא *Gemara* is, I say this גט *get*
will take effect if I don't return within twelve months. And then
there it is on the last day and I'm trying to return
but I miss the last train, or actually as there's a river
and I'm yelling and yelling and saying I'm trying to return and
trying to return. So the גמרא *Gemara* says okay but technically the
condition was met, the גט *get* is good. Okay, or do we
say that you never meant that case, you meant like you weren't
going to the condition was going to be met, you meant your
particular circumstances, in that case you never meant it and therefore the
condition is not good. So that's whether you have the טענה *ta'ana*
of אונס oness, *ones*. Hey, these were circumstances, it was act of
God, circumstances outside of my control, these weren't the circumstances that I
had in mind and therefore that overrides. That's the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* question.
Wait we had this case before and we said that it doesn't.
I know, so that's what תוספות *Tosafot* tries to figure out, like
how how's this גמרא *Gemara* in conversation with that early גמרא *Gemara*.
Okay, but that's... That's the question. So here the thinking is the
following: The guy said, "If I die מחולי זה," which we interpret
to mean "during this illness." Did he die during the illness, yes
or no, when the house fell on him? Yes. So the condition
was met. But not under the circumstances that he was intending. So
technically the condition was met, but as a result of an אונס.
oness So do we so does the אונס, oness does that mean
that it's like the condition is met or it's not like the
condition is met? So that's why שלחו מתם, shalchu mitam, they sent
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, so there we see a contradiction in
those two answers of the ברייתא. braisa One says it was met,
one said it wasn't. So is there an אונס oness claim or
not an אונס oness, claim? So שלחו מתם, they sent from ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisroel in a case like this אכלו ארי איננו. achalo
ari einenu. It did not mean to include cases of a guy
being eaten by a lion. If he died during the illness because
he was eaten by a lion, his condition was not met. He
did not die during the illness in the way that he meant
it. Okay? So that's basically it. He meant dying during the illness
under normal circumstances, not under acts of God. The בבלי, Bavli, no?
No. No. Yeah, so it's not an answer. It's basically the ברייתא
braisa is a contradiction. The גמרא's not answered the contradiction. So basically
the גמרא says these are both describing the same תנאי, one part
of the ברייתא braisa assumes that יש אונס oness, בגיטין and one
part of the ברייתא braisa assumes אין אונס oness, בגיטין. So now
we have to figure out what the הלכה halacha is. Okay? And
from ארץ ישראל they sent, acts of God don't count.
ההוא גברא. hahu gavra. Now a story.
It's true. ההוא גברא. hahu gavra. There was a certain man דזבין
ארעא לחבריה. dezavin ara lechaverei. He sold a field to his friend.
קיבל עליה כל אונסא דמיתילד. kibel alei kol onsa demisyalid. He said,
"If any if any problem happens with the field, you know, I
will I will reimburse you." Okay. לסוף אפיקו בה נהרא. lesof afiku
bah nahara. In the end, they did something that like nobody would
have expected would have happened. They redirected the course of a river
and his field flooded. Okay? So, you know, it's like when I
say anything happens, I mean if if somebody claims that if somebody
claims that the field was stolen, it winds up I never really
legally owned the field, if I don't know there's a a dam
breaks or there's flooding or whatever it might be. But that they're
going to redirect a river? Like who redirects a river? Okay. Anyway,
so that's the question. Is that a claim of אונס oness or
not? Now you could say there are different degrees of אונס, oness?
right? There's a house, you know, so anyway, but let's take a
look. אמר ליה רב אחא בר תחליפא לרבינא. amar lei Rav Acha
bar Tachlifa leRavina. I'm sorry, did I skip a line? אתא לקמיה
דרבינא. ata lekamei deRavina. Came to רבינא. Ravina. אמר ליה, amar lei,
"זיל שלים ליה, zil shalim lei, go replace the field for him.
הא קבלית עלך כל אונסא דמיתילד. ha kableit alach kol onsa demisyalid.
You said that you would accept responsibility for any אונס, ones any
circumstance that might take that might happen." אמר ליה רב אחא בר
תחליפא לרבינא, amar lei Rav Acha bar Tachlifa leRavina, "אונסא דלא שכיח
הוא. onsa dela shechiach hu. What do you mean? This is a
completely uncommon אונס, you know, it's a completely no no nobody was
expecting something as crazy as this." All right? Well, that's the question.
יש אונס או אין אונס. yesh oness o ein oness. Now there
could be a difference between גט and between and between ממון, mamon,
money. Also, there's a big difference between saying, you know, "I accept
any circumstances." That language is more language that implicitly is saying "anything."
You said "anything." As opposed to saying, "If I die from this
illness," and then something that wasn't even implicit in your words like
the house fell down. You know, so you know, that just seems
more external to the things that you're talking about. Yes. Just how
a lawyer would like a specific clause, like reasonable. Reasonable this, reasonable
that.
Right. Exactly. Or like, you know, barring acts of God. Do they
say barring acts of God anymore? Or... Yeah, airline. An airline. In
terms of replacing tickets.
Ah, insurance. Insurance, yeah. But no one argues if he says "לא
אמות." lo amut. Yes they
do. I mean, the בבלי Bavli is not recognizing... the בבלי Bavli
says "מאי שנא רישא מאי שנא סיפא." mai shna reisha mai shna
seifa. The בבלי Bavli does not recognize a difference. The בבלי Bavli
says both of those are saying "if I don't recover from this
illness," and technically speaking, in both of those, the תנאי was met.
The... and therefore the really... according to the בבלי, Bavli, it is
not about the framing of the תנאי. Technically, the תנאי was met
in both cases. The only question is a contradiction of רישא and
סיפא. Do we accept a claim of אונס or not a claim
of אונס? And does it make... does it make a difference if
he said it verbally versus writing it down? Yeah, yeah, yeah. So
let's keep... let's let's... I gotta give... we gotta get some we
gotta get some traction here. Okay,
so אמר ליה הא קביל כל אונסא. amar lei ha kibel kol
onsa. איגלגל מילתא. igalgul milta.
The matter rolled around, meaning... so it got, you know, came to
a different court. ומטא לקמיה דרבא. umata lekamei deRava. Came in front
of רבא. Rava, אמר להו, "אונסא דלא שכיח הוא." amar lehu onsa
de-lo shchiach hu, No, this is an act of God, and therefore
you don't have to reimburse. איתיביה רבינא לרבא. eiseivei Ravina leRava. רבינא
Ravina said to רבא, Rava "אם לא אעמוד מחולי זה ונפל עליו
הבית או הכישו נחש הרי זה גט." im lo amod meicholi zeh
venafal alav habayis o hichisho nachash harei zeh get. He quoted the
part of the ברייתא braisa that said it's a good גט, which
means that we right which means that we ignore the act of
God. Technically, the תנאי was met. So, so? אמר ליה רב אחא
מדיפתי לרבינא. amar lei Rav Acha miDifti leRavina.
I'm sorry, did I skip a line? הרי זה
גט. אמר ליה רבא ואימא מרישא אינו גט. amar lei Rava ve’eima
mereisha eino get. But the ברייתא braisa contradicts itself. Part of the
ברייתא braita says that we... אונס is good that we pay attention
to acts of God and part of it says we don't. So
אמר ליה רב אחא מדיפתי לרבינא, amar lei Rav Acha Mi-Difti le-Ravina,
רב אחא מדיפתי Rav Acha Mi-Difti said to רבינא, Ravina, I don't
understand, משום דקשיא רישא אסיפא לא מצינו תיובתא מינה? mishum de-kashya reisha
a-sifa lo matsinei tivta minei? Just because the ברייתא braita is self-contradictory,
we can't ask from it? Which is like, yeah! How can you
ask from it? It says contradictory things. What type of proof? You'll
bring a proof from the רישא, I'll bring a proof from the
סיפא. I like, I don't understand this. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei,
אין, yes, כיון דקשיא רישא אסיפא לא מותבינן בי מדרשא. keivan de-kashya
reisha a-sifa lo moitvei bei midrasha. Yes,
the whole thing is not a legitimate text. משבש היא, meshabbash hi,
it's a corrupt text. Okay. So, if we don't have text, זיל
בתר סברא, zil batar svara, use your logic, use your mind. If
you run out of text, use your intelligence. Okay. So, right, therefore
רבא Rava, is saying I, the ברייתא braisa. doesn't prove one way
or the other. I'm going to say acts of God are different.
Excuse me. רב פפא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע זבון שומשמי. Rav
Papa Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua zavun shumshmi. So רב פפא Rav
Papa and רב הונא, they bought like a sesame seed... wait, wait,
wait. Before the sesame seed. Yeah? Don't you think that this is
a
huge reinforcement... I knew you were going to say about that... of
what we've been talking about? Yeah, but when you run out of
text, use your mind! Well, the tension and balance between those, the
mind can go either way. There's a whole מחלוקת. machlokes. You can
even take a self-contradictory text and still פוסקן pasken from it. You're
right. I, okay, I guess for me it wasn't as huge because
I have, I know גמרות Gemaras that say even stronger things like
a גמרא says למה לי קרא סברא. lama li kra svara.
What do I need a פסוק pasuk for? I could have figured
it out myself. Right? I don't think that's as strong a statement.
Really? That's saying like a biblical verse does not add any weight
to an argument I could have made logically. Yeah, to me that
means that that פסוק pasuk is better used elsewhere where I can't
use my mind. Oh, interesting. Okay, anyway, alright, so very good. Back
to the sesame. רב פפא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע זבון שומשמי.
Rav Papa Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua zavun shumshmi. They bought sesame
seeds. אגודא דנהר מלכא, aguda de-Nahara Malka, okay, by the like bank
of the, of this river, נהר מלכא. Nahara Malka. So they had
this huge shipment of sesame seeds that they had to, it wasn't
they bought a little bag, a little shaker of sesame seeds, okay?
They're in business. They need to buy, they need to get this
done, they need to ship it, okay? אגרו מלחי, agru malchi, they
hired a shipmen, לאעבורינהו, le-avuriyu,
to bring it, you know, to transport it. קבילו עלייהו כל אונסא
דמתיליד. kibbelu aleihu kol onsa de-misyalad. Okay, now,
the, the people who, who rented the boat, who, you know, provided
the shipping service, accepted upon themselves if anything goes wrong we'll reimburse
you, gave them insurance. לסוף איסתכר נהר מלכא. le-sof istakar Nahara Malka.
In the end what happened was was that the river was dammed
up, okay, all of a sudden, this huge river, you know, and
somehow I don't know how that led to the loss of the
shipment, but whatever it was. So actually maybe it didn't lead to
the loss of the shipment. No, no, no, the point is no,
no, no, it's not that it's lost, but they now can't, they
can't get it where they need to get it, right. So אמרו
להו, amru lehu, אגורו חמרי, aguru chamri,
they said to the people who, the shippers, rent for us donkeys,
ואפתינהו ניהלן, aftei immi alan, then you know, and take it, you
know, and bring it, you know, and bring it out for us,
meaning, you know, okay, the ships are stopped up, you said you
took responsibility, go ahead, go get some donkeys.
דהא קבילו עלייכו כל אונסא דמתיליד, de-ha kibbeltu aleichu kol onsa de-misyalad,
you accepted on yourselves anything anything goes wrong. אתו לקמיה דרבא, atu
lekamei de-Rava, they came to רבא, Rava אמר להו, amar lehu, and
רבא Rava said, remember רבא Rava was the one before I think
who basically said it was an act of God, right? אמר רבא,
amar Rava, right, so yeah, and רבא Rava said אינו גט.
I'm sorry, right, רבא Rava אמר להו אונסא דלא שכיח amar lehu
onsa de-lo shchiach... הוא, it's not a... so therefore they shouldn't be...
right, right, but I'm just trying to look what did רבא Rava
say before?
אמר להו amar lehu, right above that,
אמר להו amar lehu אונסא דלא שכיח... onsa de-lo shchiach, right, right,
right. Where was that? From the previous case, from the גט case,
right? And
then let's read the end. Okay, what, yeah, what was it? Right
at the top, he says right here. You אגורו... aguru... and אתו
לקמיה דרבא אמר להו... atu lekamei de-Rava amar lehu... yes, אונסא דלא
שכיח הוא, onsa dela shechiach hu. right, there we go, exactly, thank
you. Right, so רבא Rava, beforehand had said אונסא דלא שכיח, onsa
de-lo shchiach. that it's an act of God and it's not like
the תנאי is met. So here, so he, they came to רבא,
Rava and אמר להו, amar lehu, so רבא Rava said to the
shippers now you might think that רבא Rava might side with the
rabbis against these anonymous shippers, but רבא Rava is going to say
the shippers are right, it's an אונסא דלא שכיח. So אמר להו,
amar lehu, so he said to them, קאקי חיורי, kakei chivrei, white
ducks, משלחי גלימי דאינשי, meshatchi glimei de-inshei, rip off people's shirts, meaning
he's these rabbis with their white beards think that they can go
ahead and rip off these good honest businessmen, okay? So if you
look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi says,
מפשיטים בגדי אנשים כלומר פוסקים עליהם דין אונס, mafshitim bigdei anashim klomar
porskim aleihem din anas, they think that they can go ahead, they're
rabbis and they're going to פוסקן pasken the הלכה halacha to their
own benefit. So what are they doing ripping people off? So אונסא
דלא שכיח הוא, onsa de-lo shchiach hu, I'm sorry, this was an
act of God, nobody in their right mind would have thought that
this huge river, that the, you know, that the Mississippi River was
going to get
dammed.
See I think that's more
interesting and with huge implications to different... Okay, fine. Second of all,
do you think maybe this seriously like he ripped me off? Yeah,
that I don't know. Right, I got it. Ripped the shirt off
the back, right, yeah. Okay, so when would you be responsible? What
under what circumstances would you be responsible, like what would you have
to say? Anything that normally, anything reasonable that could have that normally
are the types of things that happen that go wrong. Okay, so
is there any way to say that you're responsible for anything but
anything? Oh if you wanted, if somebody was forcing me to accept
those conditions, yeah I could say כל אונס אפילו אונס דלא שכיח,
kol onus afilu onus dlo shchiach, you know, say it explicitly if
you want to be. And that would be פסק? psak? Yeah basically
yes we do,
yes. Draw any conclusions so far as the cash on delivery and
cash back is concerned? Yeah so the simple sense of this גמרא
is that things that could not have been expected, acts of God,
are not considered to have been the satisfying the conditions. Could you
still remarry? Yes but the problem is what fits into the category
of לא שכיח, lo shchiach, what's something that if you could have
been anticipated and couldn't have been anticipated, that's a separate question. Right,
let's take a look now at the next משנה.
Okay, לא תתייחד עמו אלא בפני עדים. lo tityached imo ela bifnei
edim. So this woman now who is divorced as of now if
the husband dies, so the point is do not now continue to
live with your husband meanwhile, we don't know if he's going to
die from this חולי, don't continue to live with your husband unless
there are עדים edim present because we're afraid that what's going to
happen, he'll die, retroactively it'll be a good גט, but you'll have
now continued living with him after the day of the giving of
the גט and we'll say that that is a- no, that's a
new קידושין. kiddushin. Not גט ישן get yashan because he gave the
גט already, but people will say it's a new קידושין. kiddushin. So
the whole point was to free you from the יבם, yavam, the
brother-in-law, but if you continue living after the גט has been given,
we don't know if it's going to be valid or not, but
if it winds up retroactively even valid, you now will have a
new קידושין. kiddushin. But if there are עדים edim there then we
say there is no יחוד. yichud. אפילו על פי עבד אפילו על
פי שפחה, afilu al pi eved afilu al pi shifcha, even if
it's a slave or a slave woman, you could say that that
prevents it from being יחוד yichud and we don't therefore interpret it
like they're having sex and it's a new
קידושין. kidushin. חוץ משפחה משפחתה, chutz mishifcha mishifchatah, the
one thing that would not
make it a non-יחוד yichud situation is if it's her servant, okay
מפני שלבה גס בה בשפחתה mipnei shelibah gas bah bishifchatah because she
feels like she can just act however she wants with her you
know with her female servant. Does she count?
No, I mean it might have to be of a certain age.
Okay, מה היא באותן הימים? mah hi be'otan hayamim? So that's one
thing: don't continue living together, which is like huge, right? Number two,
what is her status? Now does she have to treat herself as
ספק מגורשת safek migureshet or you know does she just say well
right now from the first thing it sounds like she does have
to treat herself as ספק מגורשת safek migureshet and act accordingly. So
let's take a look. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says, כאשת
איש לכל דבריה, ke'eshet ish lachol devareha, she's like a married woman
for all matters, which would basically mean like כי תרומה ki Terumah
like- Michael of course thinks like the גמרא, which is right now.
Or if you take a look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says
הבא עליה במזיד בחנק ובשוגג בחטאת. haba aleha bemeizid bachenek uveshogeg bechatat.
Now the question you should be asking is what the heck are
you talking about? Retroactively she could be divorced now. So רש״י Rashi
is going to say, it's not so explicit in the גמרא, but
רש״י/גמרא is going to say reinterpret this case, although it seems very
clear that this last case is explicating the case in the previous
משנה of מהיום אם מתי. The גמרא is going to reinterpret it
or according to רש״י Rashi the גמרא is going to reinterpret it
to say that it's talking about if he basically says this should
take effect a minute before I die. Okay, that's the way רש״י
Rashi reinterprets it. So if he said it should take effect a
minute before I die, it's sort of like do תשובה teshuva the
day before you die. Since you don't know the day before you
die, you always have to do תשובה. teshuva. So if it takes
effect a minute before I die, so then the simple sense to
say is okay so any day that wasn't that in hindsight wasn't
the day before he died she was ודאי אשת איש, vadai eshet
ish, right? Whereas that's in hindsight. We say for the last three
weeks you are ודאי אשת איש, vadai eshet ish, you only became
a מגורשת migureshet on the on the day that he passed away.
Okay but that's in hindsight. But in foresight, if you're living through
those days, any day might be the day before he died and
therefore any day she's a ספק מגורשת. safek migureshet. Yeah but still
ודאי, vadai
maybe it took just all the one hour so it took- no
no no. He gave her the גט on January first. Okay? He
died on February first. During January she slept with another man. Okay,
so does she bring a חטאת? chatat? Is she- was that ודאי
vaday adultery? In hindsight it was ודאי vaday adultery. Right, in hindsight...
wait a minute! Look at the two cases. Just a scenario, okay,
in hindsight was it ודאי adultery? Yes. In foresight, it was ספק
safek adultery, right? So that's the question. Do we basically say, now
you're going to say חסרא ספוקי? chasra sefokei? but ignore that, okay?
Ask about a חטאת chatas versus an אשם, asham, right? She did
it בשוגג. be'shogeg. So do we say that now in hindsight we
say that she ודאי sinned, so she brings a חטאת? chatas? Or
do we say when she was doing it, it was a ספק
safek sin and therefore it's an אשם? asham? So that's a really
interesting question. Do we assess it in hindsight or do we assess
it בשעת מעשה? besha'as ma'aseh? I'd just say it's ספק. safek. I'd
just say she has to... she should stay... so she's not... Right,
so that's another thing. Even if we're doing it in foresight or
in present time, we should still assume the חזקה. chazaka. Right, that's
a... that is a very good question. I mean the אשת איש
eshes ish position is clearly the most obvious one. Now this is
all the way, by the way, רש"י's Rashi, read... well tomorrow I'll
tell you what תוספות's read is, okay? Right, exactly. רבי יוסי אומר
מגורשת ואינה מגורשת, Rabbi Yose omer megureshes ve'eina megureshes, she's a
ספק. safek.
So
again, for רש"י, Rashi this is a special case where he said
it'll take effect the day before I die, which has never... which
was never said in the משנה. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. תנו רבנן: ראוה שנתייחדה עמו באפילה. Ra'u'ah she'nisyachada imo ba'afeila.
So we're going first to deal with the first half of the
משנה, which is easier. Okay, so after the גט was given and
he's still on his deathbed, they were in ייחוד yichud together in
the darkness. או שישנה עמו תחת מרגלות המטה O she'yashna imo tachas
margelos hamita or
she just slept in the bedroom, but she slept like at the
foot of the bed. אין חוששין שמא נתעסקו בדבר אחר. Ein chosheshin
shema nis'asku bedavar acher.
You're not concerned that they had sex. וחוששין משום זנות. Vechosheshin mishum
znut.
But you're concerned that there was זנות. zenut. What? Okay. ואין חוששין
משום קידושין. Ve'ein chosheshin mishum kidushin.
So it sounds like, I mean it's very confusing and the גמרא's
going to try to unpack it, but it sounds like maybe in
that case they had sex, but they didn't have it for the
purpose of קידושין. kidushin. Like what? Like why should we assume that?
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אף חוששין משום קידושין. Rabbi Yose berabbi
Yehuda omer af chosheshin mishum kidushin. No, you're even concerned that there
was sex in the context of קידושין. kidushin, מאי קאמר? Mai ka'amar?
What are you talking about? So the גמרא says, אמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar
Avuha hachi ka'amar. Here's how you read this ברייתא. braisa. ראוה שנבעלה.
Ra'u'ah she'niv'ala. If they saw her have sex, if actually witnesses saw
the two of them having sex, חוששין משום קידושין. chosheshin mishum kidushin.
Then we think that that might... that could have been an act
of קידושין, kidushin. like they could have wanted it to be a
new קידושין. kidushin. The גט was given yesterday, retroactively it'll take effect,
and maybe they intended this to be a new act of קידושין.
kidushin. That is so in a simple case that they saw them
having sex, it's a ספק... safek... it's a possible קידושין. kidushin. נתן
לה כספים. Nasan lah ksafim.
Now let's say after the sex he gave her some money, he
gave her $100. So in that case חוששין משום זנות. chosheshin mishum
znut. Then we're not afraid of that קידושין. kidushin? If money changes
hands afterwards, we think that that was... she was hiring herself out.
You know this is his wife? This is his wife who he
gave a גט to yesterday. דאמרינן אתנן נתן לה. De'amrinan esnan nasan
lah. He gave it to her as her fee, as her prostitution
fee.
ואין חוששין משום... ונתן לה, ואין חוששין משום קידושין. Ve'ein chosheshin mishum...
venasan lah, ve'ein chosheshin mishum kidushin. But if money changes hands, so
the good thing is, in this case, if you don't want to
have to stop and start... if you don't want your wife to
move out of the house after you gave this גט on condition,
just give her some money every time after you have sex. Okay,
so then it won't be a ספק קידושין, safek kidushin, okay? So
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אף בזו חוששין משום קידושין. Rabbi Yose
berabbi Yehuda omer af bezo chosheshin mishum kidushin. No, maybe that was
just a gift, maybe she had to go to the store afterwards
and he gave her some money to go to the store. Okay,
so according to him that's the issue. It's only a problem of
חשש קידושין chashash kidushin if there was direct witness to them having
sex, and even... and the debate is, and if money changes hands
afterwards, does that make us reassess? Okay, so that's one read of
the ברייתא. braisa, So the גמרא says, כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן? Keman azla ha de'amar Rabba bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan? So according to that read, according to
who would go the statement in the name of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi
Yochanan: מחלוקת כשראוה שנבעלה, אבל לא ראוה שנבעלה
דברי הכל אין צריכה הימנו גט שני? Machlokes keshera'u'ah she'niv'ala, aval lo
ra'u'ah she'niv'ala divrei hakol ein tzricha heimenu get sheni? So there's a
later debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
about after a husband gives a גט to his wife, they spend
the night in the inn. Are we concerned that that's a new
act of קידושין? kidushin. Sounds very relevant to this case. Okay, so
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan there says the whole debate of בית הלל
Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai is when they saw that
the couple had sex. But if they didn't see the couple had
sex, דברי הכל אין צריכה גט שני, divrei hakol ein tzricha get
sheni, there's no concern of קידושין. kiddushin, So that's very consistent with
this read. This read is it only begins to be a possible
issue if they actually directly witnessed the sex. So who's that going
like? So the גמרא says, one minute... so the גמרא says, כמאן?
Keman? Who's that going like? כדברי הכל. Kedivrei hakol. According to this
read of the ברייתא, braisa it's this ברייתא Braita is going to
whether בית הלל Beis Hillel or whether בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, according
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, because according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that whole debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis
Shammai only begins once they actually saw them having sex, and you're
saying the same thing here, that if they were never seen to
have sex, just because they were seen in ייחוד, yichud, there would
not be a problem. Okay, let's just read a little bit further.
Okay. So the גמרא says like this, that's read number one. מתקיף
לה אביי, Maskif lei Abaye, אביי Abaye asked, מידי כספא קתני? Midi
kaspah katani? Since when does this ברייתא Braita? mention money? Like how
do you read that into the ברייתא? Braita. אלא אמר אביי הכי
קאמר, Ela amar Abaye hachi ka-amar, here's how you read this ברייתא.
Braita. ראוהו שנבעלה, Ra-uhu she-niv'ala, they saw her having sex, חוששין משום
זנות chosheshin mishum zenut ואין חוששין משום קידושין. ve-ein chosheshin mishum kiddushin.
That sounds like a better read of the ברייתא. Braita. We're not
concerned, סתם stam you see sex, we're not concerned that it's an
act of קידושין, kiddushin. they're just having sex outside the context of
marriage. If wine tasted good, then this was not meant as a
new act of קידושין. kiddushin. So that's the first opinion in the
ברייתא. Braita. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אף חוששין משום קידושין. Rabbi
Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda omer af chosheshin mishum kiddushin. No, if they were
seen to have had sex, that might be a קידושין. kiddushin Okay,
but again, the whole problem begins if they were witnessed to have
sex. So again, כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן מחלוקת כשראוהו שנבעלה אבל לא ראוהו שנבעלה דברי הכל אינה
צריכה הימנו גט שני. ke-man azla ha d'amar Rabba bar bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yochanan machloket k'sherauhu she-niv'ala aval lo ra-uhu she-niv'ala divrei ha-kol
einah tzericha heimenu get sheni. That if there is no witnessing of
the sex, everybody agrees that there's no need for a גט. כמאן?
Ke-man? כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. ke-Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda. Oh, that goes
like, that's רבי יוסי... Rabbi Yose... oh right, I'm sorry, that's רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda because this is saying because
according to this, according to right, if they did see them having
sex, right, even then there the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says it's
not a problem, it's a זנות. zenut. Only רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda says is it a ספק קידושין. safek kiddushin.
So according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says that when בית הלל, Beit Hillel, basically בית הלל Beit Hillel
says that there's a ספק קידושין, safek kiddushin, if they... I mean
to say בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's a קידושין kiddushin. in
that later discussion, that would be only according to רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda. Right here, right, is it understood like
בית הלל בית שמאי Beit Hillel Beit Shammai say they spent the
night in the פונדק pundak (inn), and בית הלל Beit Hillel says
that it might be קידושין. kiddushin? And now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says that's when they were witnessed having sex. So the גמרא says,
okay, who is it that says that when they were witnessed to
having sex it's a ספק קידושין? safek kiddushin? According to this, it's
only רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda, because the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says even if they're witnessed having sex, we're just
going to interpret it as זנות. zenut Okay, so מתקיף לה רבא,
maskif lei Rava, but that's the read of the ברייתא. Braita. Now
רבא asked on this, אם כן מאי אף? im ken mai af?
Why does it say in רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that אף חוששין
משום קידושין, af chosheshin mishum kiddushin, we're also concerned it might be
קידושין? kiddushin, No, זנות zenut, is a קולא. kula. He shouldn't say
it also might be קידושין, kiddushin. it says we don't have the
קולא kula of זנות, zenut. we're saying it's קידושין. kiddushin. אלא אמר
רבא הכי קאמר, Ela amar Rava hachi ka-amar, here's how to read
the ברייתא. Braita. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אף לא ראוהו שנבעלה.
Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda omer af lo ra-uhu she-niv'ala. I agree with
you, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying if they saw them
having sex, still not a problem, זנות. zenut. And רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda is saying אף לא ראוהו שנבעלה. af
lo ra-uhu she-niv'ala. I'm going to tell you something, number one, you're
wrong. If they saw them having sex, it is a ספק קידושין.
safek kiddushin. But number two, even if they weren't witnessed to having
sex, as long as they were together, חוששין משום קידושין, chosheshin mishum
kiddushin, as long as they were in ייחוד yichud together like our
משנה sounds like, even that would be a concern. So you have
exact opposite positions, which is a nice read of the ברייתא. תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says witnessed having sex, even that's not a problem,
we assume זנות. And רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda
says even just being in ייחוד yichud together, we assume קידושין. kiddushin.
So the גמרא says and finally כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן מחלוקת כשראוהו שנבעלה אבל לא ראוהו שנבעלה
דברי הכל אינה צריכה הימנו גט. ke-man azla ha d'amar Rabba bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan machloket k'sherauhu she-niv'ala aval lo ra-uhu she-niv'ala
divrei ha-kol einah tzericha heimenu get. So what about רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan's statement? That he says that if they weren't witnessed having sex,
בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, nobody says it's
a problem. Here you're saying that according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda, if they weren't witnessed to having sex it
is a problem. Right? Everybody get that? So כמאן דלא כחד. ke-man
d'lo k'chad. Fine, that doesn't work with רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda because רבי יוסי... Rabbi Yose... so we basically have
a whole range of positions from the weird one which is it's
never a problem unless, you know, it's a problem with sex unless
money changes hands, like who's talking about money? But the basic two
approaches is, one read is if they were witnessed having sex it's
a not a problem, and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi
Yehuda says no, if they were witnessed having sex it's a ספק
קידושין. safek kiddushin. To the final read of that one opinion says
it's never a problem, even witnessed having sex, and רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yose bi-Rabbi Yehuda says even just being in ייחוד yichud
together we assume קידושין. When do we are concerned about a ספק
קידושין safek kiddushin because they're either living together ייחוד yichud or having
sex, and reading that as a range of positions from we're never
concerned to we're always concerned. Okay, we will end here.